Hello English learners, welcome
back to English Pod, my name is Marco.
And I'm Erica.
And today we have
a very special lesson
because we're going to be
focusing a little bit more on grammar.
That's right.
We're going to look today at
the difference between past simple
and past progressive or
sometimes called past continuous.
Exactly.
So we're going to take a look at these two
structures which are a little bit confusing
at times and we're going
to be practicing today.
But before we get started, why don't
we take a look at vocabulary preview?
vocabulary preview.
Well, this dialogue is all
about telling a story in the past.
And we're going to
hear two words in the
dialogue that we need to
understand the meaning of.
So the first one ages ages,
I haven't seen you in ages.
Okay, so if I tell you
I haven't seen you in
ages, basically you haven't
seen me in a really long time.
Okay.
So it's a way of exaggerating a little bit.
Yes.
And this word ages we
can use in many different
ways like I've been
studying English for ages.
Or for example, I can say I
haven't been to the dentist in ages.
Ooh.
Well, guess you better go.
Right, so ages a very long time.
Yes.
Now another phrase to run into somebody.
So to run into somebody.
I ran into Matt.
Okay, so if you ran into Matt the
other day, you met him unexpectedly.
Okay, so you didn't
plan to meet, you didn't
have a date just
casually on the street met.
Exactly.
So I ran into your friend the other day.
Okay.
So two good words are going to
hear both of these in the dialogue.
So why don't we get started
with dialogue first time?
Mike, what's going on man?
Long time.
Hey, Pat.
Yeah, I haven't seen you in ages.
How's it going?
Things are going great.
It's funny running it to you like this.
Small world.
You know, just last week
I ran into Matt as well.
Yeah.
How's he doing?
He's doing well.
We went up for a couple of beers
and the funniest thing happened.
Oh, yeah.
Well, we were talking and catching up on
what we've been doing, talking about work
and family and all of
a sudden Matt saw a
mouse run into the chair
and he completely lost
it.
He started freaking in screaming.
Really?
Yeah, and the funniest
thing was, then he
jumped onto his chair and
started shrieking like a girl.
He should have been there.
Everyone was staring and laughing.
It was hilarious.
Alright, very good.
So a funny story and as we saw
a lot of stuff in the past, right?
That's right.
And we're going to
look at that in a moment,
but first we've got lots
of exciting language
to describe when somebody
gets really emotional.
Okay.
So why don't we start now
with language takeaway?
Language takeaway.
We have four words here.
Now, in a dialogue, the
guy in the story lost it.
So he saw a mouse and he
completely lost it to lose it.
Okay.
So when you lose some, you lose it.
What are you losing?
You're losing control of
yourself and your emotion.
Okay.
So you lose your temper maybe.
Yep.
So when I lose it, do I just
get angry, angry or upset
or even sad, but it's
usually a negative feeling.
Okay.
So it's not a good thing to lose it.
No.
So for example, when I showed my boss
the sales figures, he completely lost it.
Okay.
Very good.
So that's what lose it means.
And now our second word is very similar,
but has a little bit of a difference.
That's right.
He started freaking out.
Okay.
So to freak out.
To freak out.
Now, freak out is very
similar to lose it, right?
Yeah.
But why don't we hear an example now of
somebody freaking out is just, no, no, okay.
Forget it.
All right.
Just forget it.
I don't even want to, just, I just want
to forget it, I just want to forget it.
I don't know, I don't know.
Okay.
Come down.
Woo.
I got to come down.
I'm so happy again.
I can't even express it.
I'm like, I haven't.
Have I even finished one sentence?
I'm like, oh, give me a high five, baby.
All right.
So we heard this
person freaking out and
basically it could be
losing control or losing
your temper, but
also in a positive way.
Right.
So maybe you're really
excited about something
that's going to happen,
so you're freaking out.
Okay.
Maybe you're very nervous.
So you're very excited.
Mm hmm.
And now moving on to
our third word, stare to stare.
People started to stare.
Staring.
Okay.
Now, when you stare at
someone or at something,
you look at and focus at
something for a really long time.
Okay.
So you are looking at it.
Yeah.
I'm focusing on it.
Longer than usual.
All right.
Maybe when we were
small, our parents taught
us that it's not nice to
stare at other people.
Exactly.
All right.
They're in our final words.
When Matt saw the
mouse, he started shrieking.
All right.
So too shriek, shriek, shriek,
very similar to that movie.
Shrek.
Oh, yeah.
Sounds quite similar.
All right.
But it's different.
What does shriek mean?
Well, why don't we listen to an example?
Whoo!
Oh my god.
Hallelujah.
Okay.
So I think shrieking is too
shout in a very high pitched voice.
Exactly.
That's too shriek.
Okay.
So we saw four really great
words in language takeaway.
And why don't we listen now to the dialogue
for a second time a little bit slower.
And then we'll come back
and look at the differences
between simple past
and past progressive.
Mike, what's going on, man?
Long time no see.
Hey, Pat.
Yeah.
I haven't seen you in ages.
How's it going?
Things are going great.
It's funny running into you like this.
Small world, eh?
You know, just last week,
I ran into Matt as well.
Yeah?
How's he doing?
He's doing well.
We went out for a couple of beers
and the funniest thing happened.
Oh, yeah?
Well, we were talking and catching up on
what we've been doing, talking about work
and family, when all
of a sudden, Matt saw a
mouse run under his chair
and he completely lost it.
He started freaking
out and screaming, haha.
Really?
Yeah.
And the funniest thing
was that he jumped on
his chair and started
shrieking like a girl.
You should have been there.
Everyone was staring and laughing.
It was hilarious.
Okay, so there was a lot of different
uses of past tense here in this dialogue.
Wasn't there?
Yes.
Since he was telling a story that
happened, he used the past a lot.
Well, let's now, as
promised, look at past
simple and past progressive
in grammar breakdown.
Rama breakdown.
Okay, Marko, before
we start our discussion,
why don't we hear one example of past
simple and one example of past progressive?
You know, just last week,
I ran into Matt as well.
Well, we were talking and catching
up on what we've been doing.
Okay, so we heard
that just last week I ran
into Matt, so we discussed
what run into means.
Yep.
To meet someone by surprise.
All right.
And now this structure
is the simple past, right?
Yep.
One example that we heard was
we were talking and catching up.
Okay, so let's look at the
difference in meaning here.
I ran into Matt, happened
in the past, right?
Right.
Simple past.
But one moment in the past.
So the action finished, concluded.
Started and finished all
around the same time.
So it's one simple moment.
Okay.
Now the other example
is in the past progressive.
So the action was happening
for a longer period of time.
Yeah.
Okay.
So let's, let's attach some times to this.
Maybe you ran into Matt at 804, okay?
And so the action started
at 804, but you were
talking and catching
up from 805 until 905.
Okay.
So you were talking for an hour.
Right.
So the past progressive,
you use when you're,
when the action is happening
for a longer period of time.
Okay.
So to better understand this,
let's have another example.
Matt saw a mouse run under
his chair and he completely lost it.
Everyone was staring and laughing.
So as we heard in the example,
he saw a mouse run under his chair.
So a quick action that
started and finished quickly.
Okay.
He saw the mouse and
it ran under the chair.
Yep.
Now the second example we heard
was, everyone was staring and laughing.
So maybe this happened
over four or five minutes.
Okay.
So people were looking
at him and laughing and
talking about how he
was screaming like a girl.
Yes.
Okay.
So that's the main
difference between the
simple past and the past progressive, the
amount of time that the action happened.
Yep.
All right.
Well, now that we
understand a little bit more
about the past tense,
why don't we hear it
again, in context by listening
to the dialogue for a third time.
Mike, what's going on, man?
One time no see.
Hey, Pat.
Yeah.
I haven't seen you in ages.
How's it going?
Things are going great.
It's funny running into you like this.
Small world, huh?
You know, just last week
I ran into Matt as well.
Yeah?
How's he doing?
He's doing well.
Not for a couple of beers and the
funniest thing happened, really, yeah?
Well, we were talking
and catching up on
what we've been doing,
talking about work and
family and all of a
sudden, Matt saw a mouse
run into the chair and
he completely lost it.
He started freaking in screaming.
Really?
Yeah.
And the funniest thing
was, then he jumped onto
his chair and started
shrieking like a girl.
He should have been there.
Everyone was staring and laughing.
It was hilarious.
Ha ha.
Okay.
Perfect.
So now that we understand
the words and the
grammar behind it,
there are some interesting
phrases here that you can
use casually with your friends.
Yeah.
There's actually a
lot of great sort of
meeting and greeting
and saying hello language.
So for example, when
they met up, since they
were old friends, he
said, "Hey, Pat, hey.
" Okay.
So this word, "Hey.
" It's kind of like high.
It's high, right?
Yep.
So if you use it to get somebody's
attention, right, like, "Hey, I'm over here.
" Hey, waiter.
Okay.
Yeah.
But in this case, like,
"Hey, how's it going?
" Hi.
Yeah.
So it's a really friendly and
informal way of saying, "Hi.
" Okay.
And then he asked,
"How's it going?
" How is it going?
So again, this is a way
of saying, "How are you?
" Yeah.
Marco, what's the correct
answer to this greeting?
Well, well, for example, he
said things are going great.
Right?
You can say, "Yeah, things
are great or I'm doing well."
Yeah.
Even great.
Great.
Yeah.
So how's it going?
Oh, it's great.
Yeah.
Right?
Now, another one
that we didn't see in the
dialogue, but it's very popular is
when somebody asks, "Hey, what's up?
" Yeah.
What's up?
So, again, what is the right
way to answer this question?
All right.
So when somebody says, "What's up?"
You can say, "Well, not much," or if maybe
you have news or something that you want
to share, you would say, "Well, I
just got back from the doctor's office."
Yep.
But you wouldn't say, "Fine, thank you,"
or you wouldn't say, "Very good," or any
of these other common
answers to, "What's up?"
That's right.
It can be a little bit tricky.
Yeah.
So the rule is, the normal thing to say
when someone says, "Hey, what's up?"
It's nothing much.
Not much.
Yep.
All right.
So interesting ways of greeting
casually with people, right?
You wouldn't use this with your
boss, maybe, or in an office setting.
Yep.
More useful with your friends.
Okay.
So if you have any other questions or have
any other informal greetings that you would
like to share with us,
come to EnglishPod.com.
Yeah, Marco and I are
always around to answer
your questions, and we look
forward to hearing from you.
So until next time.
Bye.